<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration from the Commission of the General Assembly wherein the stumblng blocks laid before the people of God by their enemies are removed, complyance with these enemies is reprehended, and courage and constancie in the cause of God against them seriously recommended and enjoyned.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26023</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09316767</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09316767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1305:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration from the Commission of the General Assembly wherein the stumblng blocks laid before the people of God by their enemies are removed, complyance with these enemies is reprehended, and courage and constancie in the cause of God against them seriously recommended and enjoyned.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Glasgow University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly. --  Commission.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION FROM THE <hi>COMMISSION</hi> OF The Generall Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Wherein The ſtumbling blocks laid before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD by their enemies are removed; Complyance with theſe enemies is reprehended; And Courage and conſtancie in the Cauſe of GOD againſt them, ſeriouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and enjoyned.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH: Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:42734:2"/>
            <head>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Andr. 26. Decemb. 1645.</head>
            <p>THe Eſtates of Parliament now conveened in the fift Seſsion of this firſt triennall Parliament, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard the Declaration preſented unto them by the Commiſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly read in their audience, received the ſamen cheerfully as a ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Declaration, and appoints the ſamen to be Printed and publiſhed, and ordains the Earle of Caſsils Vice Preſident of Parliament, to give thanks from the Parliament to the Commiſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly for their care, pains, and vigilancie expreſt thereintill.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alex. Gibſone Cler. Regiſtri.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <head>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Andr. 11. Decemb. 1645.</head>
            <p>THe Commiſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly Do Ordain this Declaration to be forthwith Printed and publiſhed, and ſent to Presbyteries with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and requires each Presbytery immediatly after the receit thereof, to take ſpeedie courſe for the reading of it in every congregation within their bounds upon the Lords day after the Forenoon Sermon and before the Bleſsing; And that they report account of their diligence herein with the firſt conveniencie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42734:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Andrews 11. Decemb. 1645.</hi> A Declaration from the Commiſsion of the Generall Aſſembly.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been our conſtant cuſtome and continuall care, from the ſence of the truſt committed unto us, to give warning unto this Kirk and Kingdom of their condition and dutie; and it cannot be but very ſeaſonable and neceſſary at this time, to declare and make known our judgement of the carriage of the people of the Land, in the day of darkneſſe and hour of temptation, that they who have ſtood may finde matter of encouragement and praiſe, and ſuch as have fallen may recover themſelves and repent.</p>
            <p>We were void of underſtanding if we ſhould not obſerve, and more then ungrate if we ſhould not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the loving kindneſſe of the Lord towards us, in the midſt of our confuſions and fears: Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations were many and fierce, becauſe of the power and pride of an inſolent enemy, whoſe blaſphemies and crueltie is matter of abomination unto this, and ſhall be a wonder unto the following generation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42734:3"/> yet was there a remnant who reſerved their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, entertaining all thoughts of backſliding and complying with the adverſary with indignation and deteſt, patiently ſuffering the ſpoiling of their goods, the loſſe of their friends, and expence of their blood, ſtanding to the Cauſe of God in the midſt of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and ſtraits, neither fearing the threats nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the promiſes of ſuch as oppoſe the famine: Theſe, as they be for a name of joy and praiſe unto the moſt high, the excellencie of whoſe power is perfited in weakneſſe; ſo for a witneſſe unto the Truth and to the work of Reformation, and for a ſhame and reproach unto the haters of Zion, whoſe ſubtilty and violence is more then conquered by the faith and patience of the Saints. We cannot but think that unto ſuch the teſtimony of integrity from within muſt needs be more comfortable, then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of any ſufferings or loſſes from without can be grievous; and are perſwaded, that as their name is precious amongſt men, ſo ſhall their reward be great in heaven.</p>
            <p>Yet is it matter of much ſorrow and aſtoniſhment unto us, that in the land of uprightneſſe ſo many ſhould have done fooliſhly, and notwithſtanding of all that work of power and mercy which their eyes have ſeen, and of their own vows and promiſes fallen from their excellencie, and turned aſide unto corrupt and crooked wayes with the workers of iniquity. The bond of the Covenant is ſuch, as every religious heart cannot but remember the violation thereof with horrour and trembling; yet hath the Oath of God been forgotten and deſpiſed by many. It were but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42734:3"/> the renewing of our grief, and tedious unto the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to reckon up all thoſe things wherein men miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried in the day of tryall; neither can we attain the knowledge of all the hidden things of diſhoneſty, which hate the light, and love to vail themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſhadow of ſecrecie and darkneſſe: We deſire every man to turn his eyes upon himſelf, and to read in his own conſcience whether his carriage hath been in all things anſwerable unto that which he ſwore unto the Lord. It beſeems our compaſſion, and is worthy of our care, to lay open the cauſes and evil of this defection, <hi>that we may with meekneſſe inſtruct thoſe that</hi> have fallen or <hi>oppoſed themſelves, if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure will give them repentance unto the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the admirable way of the working of the wiſdome of God, to over-rule all the purpoſes and actions of the ſons of men unto his own ends: He whoſe wayes towards us have all been mercy and trueth, meant a diſcoverie of thoſe whoſe indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or treachery would ere long have procured a ſure and ſenſible ruine unto us; and now hath he brought his purpoſe to paſſe. This is a mercy which being rightly managed may countervail all our ſufferings and pains, and prove very wholſome unto the Land and advantagious unto the Cauſe of God.</p>
            <p>It is not any ſtrength of reaſon on the ſide of our adverſaries that could have ſhaken ſo many; their pretexts of the Kings ſervice, our Rebellion, and ſuch like, as they are poore and void of trueth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo do they eaſily evaniſh before every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning and rationall man. The ſervice of Kings is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42734:4"/> not to cut down thouſands of their faithfull and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubjects, whoſe multitude is their glory and ſtrength; but to do thoſe things which the Laws of the Kingdom preſcribe, and that are conſonant unto the will of God, and unto the wealth of the people, whoſe ſafety is the ſupream Law and main ſtudie of every King ruling in righteouſneſſe and judgement. Our ſouls are not privie unto, and our actions plead us innocent from the guilt of Treaſon and Rebellion; <hi>our witneſſe is in heaven, and our record is on high,</hi> that it was never our purpoſe or intention to ſubvert law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraigntie, nor to encroach upon any of the due rights and priviledges of the ſame; and we truſt that whiles we live nothing ſhall eſcape us to the contrary.</p>
            <p>We are able to juſtifie our union with <hi>England,</hi> as ane undenyable teſtimonie of our dutie unto our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the time of their ſtraits by the Popiſh and Prelaticall partie, as a neceſſary mean of our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and of the preſervation of Religion in its purity and power in this, and of its Reformation in the neighbour Lands, and ſureſt bulwark of a ſtable and continuing peace betwixt the Kingdoms. The League and Covenant with <hi>England,</hi> as it was ſtudied and ſet on foot in the dayes of our fathers at <hi>Barwick</hi> in the yeer 1586; ſo was it from the beginning of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work of Reformation endeavoured by our ſelves, as ſtands upon record in the Articles of the large Treatie, unto which ſome of thoſe who have now fallen to oppoſe it, were then neither ſtrangers nor adverſaries. Both Covenants, in regard of the principals whence they iſſue, the heads which they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42734:4"/> contain, and the ends which they purſue, are one and the ſame: And that the extent of the laſt unto our dear brethren in <hi>England</hi> ſhould procure enmitie to the intentions and ſubſtance of the firſt, ſeems to us to be a riddle, which none can reſolve but perfidious Rebels who have made ſhipwrack of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Who can but be amazed to hear the treacherous deſignes and bloody practiſes of perjured men, palliat under a pretence of the proſecution of the ends of our nationall Covenant: We know that <hi>James Grahame</hi> then Earle of <hi>Montroſe,</hi> now an excommunicate and forefaulted Traitour, did with tears in his eyes, and both his hands lifted up to heaven, ſwear unto the Lord in the publike aſſembly of his people to build thoſe things which he now deſtroyes, and to deſtroy thoſe things which he now builds; though the Kings Majeſtie, of whoſe authority he now pretends to be ſo zealous, had not then given his royall conſent and approbation unto our affairs: But we do as well know that he proved unſtable, and light as water: His am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as it made him impatient of his own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the eſtimation of thoſe of better deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then himſelf, ſo to hearken to the promiſes of the Court, and to ſtudie a faction within, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſecret correſpondence and intelligence with the adverſe partie without the Kingdom. And though thoſe his baſe and treacherous wayes were divers times diſcovered, yet did he ſtill drive his own croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deſignes, untill at length he was ſhut up in priſon, where if he had not met with more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie then juſtice, the due reward of his iniquitie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42734:5"/> had anticipate all that miſchiefe which hee now acts.</p>
            <p>Not long after his enlargement (contrary to his own promiſe and Act of Parliament thereanent) he betook himſelf to Court, where to the utmoſt of his wit and power he did foment and maintain that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and bloody War, ſet on foot by the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant partie in <hi>England,</hi> againſt his Majeſties loyall ſubjects there, contrary to the Articles of the large Treatie betwixt the Kingdoms; and laboured to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and increaſe jealouſies in the Kings minde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the intention of his ſubjects in this land: Neither did he ſatisfie himſelf with private whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but was ſo impudent as to preſent to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and the pretended Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> a railing Libell, wherein he accuſeth our Parliaments and Committees (which have been in all things moſt tender of the Kings juſt greatneſſe and authority) as treacherous in their proceedings, and the ſolemne League and Covenant (which hath been a mean of many bleſſings and much conſolation unto the Lords people) as damnable, Offering himſelf and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his endeavours againſt the ſame; And never did he ceaſe untill he obtained a Commiſſion for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading his native Countrey, and came within the confines thereof in an hoſtile way; whence he was ſhamefully repulſed and forced to flee back into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where he found cold entertainment of his own partie, becauſe his ſucceſſe had not anſwered his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings.</p>
            <p>Whileſt himſelf was now deſpiſed, and his hopes forlorn in both Nations, this Kingdome was invaded
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42734:5"/> in the North by a baſe and barbarous Crue of Iriſh Rebels, drunk with the bloud of our Brethren in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſworn enemies, not onely to our Covenant, but to our Profeſſion it ſelf: yet ſo ſtrongly did the ſpirit of Satan (to whom he was now delivered) work in that wretched Man, that he did rather chooſe to aſſociat himſelf unto thoſe, than to fail in the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his miſchievous ends. With thoſe, and ſome of our unnaturall Countreymen, void of Religion and humanitie, hath he eaten the fleſh, and drunk the bloud of that Land that gave him life, ſpoyled that People with whom he was in Covenant, and preyed upon that Church in which he was baptized: neglect of the worſhip of God, countenancing of Idolaters, comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Papiſts, burning of Houſes and Corn, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning and killing of Miniſters, raviſhing of Women, murdering of old and young, and contemning the higheſt cenſures of the Kirk, are but things of ſmall conſequence and care with him: This is the Man who would make the world believe, that he ſtands for the Nationall Covenant: Every one whoſe eyes are not blinded by the god of this world, cannot but entertain this his Profeſſion, ſo contrary to ſenſe and reaſon, with deriſion and contempt.</p>
            <p>Succeſſe, as it argues not the equitie of our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cauſe, ſo neither the iniquitie of ours: <hi>No man knowes either love or hatred by that which is before him:</hi> Succeſſe is not the touch-ſtone of Truth, but Truth of Succeſſe: Iſrael may fall before the Philiſtims; yea, the Ark may be taken by the Philiſtims: And what wonder though we have fallen, &amp; been ſmitten by the baſeſt of men? they were the <hi>rod of the Lords anger,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42734:6"/> the ſtaff in their hand was his indignation; becauſe of our contempt of the Goſpel, ingratitude, confidence in the arm of fleſh, murmurings and repinings, delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Juſtice, walking unanſwerable to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the like, were ſuch inſtruments armed againſt us, to correct us, and harden themſelves unto the day of their juſt deſtruction.</p>
            <p>For theſe <hi>tranſgreſsions alſo of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and for</hi> theſe <hi>ſins of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, did the Lord ſhut out our prayers, and cover himſelf with a cloud of indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that our Petitions could not paſſe through; and not for medling with the Kings Caſtles and Rents: His Caſtles have alwayes been imployed for the ſafetie of the Kingdome; his Rents have not been medled with ſince the Pacification, neither yet before it, but for a publick uſe, which was afterward approven by the King himſelf. And they who would now faſten this upon us, as a curſed thing, may remember that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were acceſſorie thereunto. Neither yet were our Prayers without a return of mercy in the day of our deepeſt diſtreſſe: The Work of Reformation (which is of greater eſteem with us than our own things) did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in the hand of his ſervants; and we truſt, that even theſe Prayers which were derided by the wicked, ſhall in due time return in ſhowres of vengeance upon the heads of our enemies, whereof we have already com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable experience.</p>
            <p>It is our hearts deſire and hope, that all this courſe of providence, thus abuſed by men void of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, may be improven by our ſelves as a mean of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſound humiliation, that we may ſearch and try our wayes, and turn again unto the Lord, who will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42734:6"/> do good unto us, becauſe of the railing of our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; notwithſtanding of all calumnies and reproaches, the righteouſneſſe of our cauſe ſhall be counted of us our glory, and in regard of it, <hi>we will not remove our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie from us: our righteouſneſſe we will ſtill hold faſt, and not let it go, and our heart ſhall not reproach us ſo long as we live; yea, though our adverſaries would write a book againſt us, ſurely we would take it on our ſhoulder, and bind it as a crown unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true and real cauſes of our back-ſliding are to be ſought amongſt our ſelves. If all the Watchmen of the houſe of Iſrael had bin faithful &amp; zealous in diſcharge of their truſt, then had the Lords people better known the excellency of the Goſpel, &amp; ſtuck cloſer to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the ſame; becauſe of the negligence and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſnes of ſome of thoſe, have many halted for want of inſtruction &amp; lack of knowledge; but from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which men have harboured in their own breaſts, hath mainly iſſued all the degrees of their declination.</p>
            <p>There be amongſt us many rotten and hollow hearts, who though they joyned with us through ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie or fear, did ſtill abide <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe, and bond of iniquity,</hi> and wiſhed nothing more, than the ſubverſion of our cauſe: What wonder though ſuch took advantage of a prevailing party, to diſcloſe their envy, wherewith they were now growne big, almoſt unto burſting: And there is a generation whoſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſloath hath detained them, that they have not ſufficiently examined, nor rightly conſidered Zions controverſie with thoſe that plead againſt her, becauſe of her love to the Truth: They conceive the debate to be about things civil; at leaſt, not to go ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42734:7"/> high as the hazard of any thing important in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And ſuch is the negligence of thoſe, that they deſpiſe the meanes of inſtruction, largely offered and holden forth unto them in many Warnings and Declarations, which they will not be at the pains to peruſe: Love to the things of the world, hath ſtumbled men of earthly mindes, who had rather chooſe to endanger their ſouls, and make ſhipwrack of a good conſcience, than to ſuffer the ſpoyling of their Goods, and ruine of their Eſtates: And Atheiſme prevailes in many, which as it is not acquainted with the excellencie of JESUS CHRIST, nor with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe and ſweetneſſe of his wayes, ſo hath it no regard to his Commandments to obey them, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Goſpel, to ſuffer any thing for it. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formalitie and profanitie abounds, is it not juſt with GOD to ſend them ſtrong deluſion to <hi>believe lies,</hi> who do not receive the Truth in love. And what if ſome being puft up in mind, have truſted to the power of their own ſtrength, and neglected to imploy that mighty One, upon whom our help is laid.</p>
            <p>Though we cannot but think, that all ſuch as are not given up to deluſion and hardneſſe of heart, have already begun to conſider the evill of their wayes, and to remember their inconſtancie with deteſtation and ſorrow; yet, for convincing of the obſtinate, reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the more flexible, and increaſing of the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thoſe who deſire to loathe themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their back-ſliding, we cannot but diſcover the guiltineſſe that many involved themſelves into, in the houre of temptation that came upon the Land. As
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42734:7"/> there be degrees of duties in the Covenant, ſo degrees of offences againſt the ſame: We would have none ſo groſſe to plead innocencie, becauſe they have not broke forth in open oppoſition: Indifferencie and neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralitie is no leſſe againſt our Oath, then profeſſed enimitie: And what alſo if it be as odious in the ſight of GOD, who ſpues the lukewarme out of his mouth? How then ſhall we judge of back-ſliding and expreſſe malignancie? Surely diſobedience unto pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick order, or prevarication in the ſame, commending of adverſaries their purpoſe, power, or carriage, tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Inſtruments and Work of Reformation, be but the bitter fruits of an evill heart, diſ-affected to the truth, &amp; cleaving to the love of the paths of thoſe, who ſtudy the obſtruction and diſ-appointment of all thoſe ends deſigned in the Covenant: Silence when we had a calling to ſpeak: Setting on of Bonfires: Preparing entertainment for the Rebels, and receiving them into our Houſes, are but at the beſt ſinfull temporizing in an evill time, a betraying of our zeal for the Lord, a ſtrengthening of the ungodly in their wicked courſes, and yeelding unto them a ground of hope for further complying with them, and an high contempt of the dreadfull ſentence of Excommunication, if any of thoſe with whom fellowſhip was kept, were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame: Intelligence and correſpondence with the Enemie, furniſhing them with Men, Money, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Ammunition, or Cloathes, ſeducing of the people, receiving Commiſſions, or executing the ſame, and joyning in actuall ſervice. Thoſe things if done out of affection, and not through fear, as ſome of them hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can be, are ſure tokens of a heart deſperatly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42734:8"/> and wholly malignant, which eſteems it but a light thing to hazard upon expreſſe perjury, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever done, draw upon the doers a manifeſt breach of Covenant, and fearfull guilt of helping thoſe whom the Lord hates.</p>
            <p>What though it be lawfull in ſome caſes to capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, yea with Turks or Pagans; ſhall it therefore be lawfull to do that which may argue ſubjection and imply ſubmiſſion unto a perfidious Rebell, and the ſworn enemy of the League and Covenant with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, going about to drive the people of the Land from their dutie for the Covenant, to a complyance with him againſt it. In this caſe, all &amp; every one are called unto the aſſerting of the confeſſion of their Faith, and of their own innocencie and righteouſneſſe in joyning with England; Both which they do betray and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, and take with that guiltineſſe of Treaſon and Rebellion, which the Adverſaries would faſten upon them, when they capitulate to do any thing inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with open and profeſt enimitie, or that tends un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſſerting of thoſe duties to which the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant doth oblige them: Such Capitulations muſt needs be very ſinfull, and contrary to the Covenant. Neither can we judge any better of Protections from ſuch an Enemy becauſe they do imply the authority of one who is forfeit by the State, and excommunicat by the Kirk; and do either expreſſely or tacitely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Receivers, if not to joyne, yet not to reſiſt; they lay a ſtumbling block before all the Inhabitants of the Land, to make them forbear action, or decline ſuffering, by following ſuch a courſe: If all had done ſo, it may ſoon be foreſeen what ſhould have been the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42734:8"/> end; Though haply they who were the doers, were not ſo apprehenſive as to reach the depth of the evill, yet the end of the work in it ſelf, and in the intention of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, was to make them Maſters of all the lives and eſtates within the Land.</p>
            <p>Capitulations and Protections, howſoever accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by thoſe who walk after the wiſedome of the fleſh, are deſtructive to our Covenant, almoſt in all the Heads and Articles thereof: They tend unto the corrupting of Religion in this Land, and obſtructing the Work of Reformation in England, unto the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and ſtrengthening of the Popiſh and Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall party, unto the ſubverſion of the due Rights and Priviledges of the Parliaments, and diminiſhing of his Majeſties juſt greatneſſe and authority, unto the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of Incendiaries and Malignants from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment, unto the overthrow of the Union betwixt the Kingdoms, unto the deſerting of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, following of diviſive motions, and denying to hazard or ſuffer the loſſe either of lives or eſtates in the defence of the Cauſe, and them that adhere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Wee ſee not any ſtrength of reaſon in that ſeeming neceſſity, unto which many pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have been redacted: If men could not have retired from the fury and violence of the Enemy, or had not ſome probable way of reſiſtance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the ſame, they ſhould have taken it as an evidence of the will of GOD, calling them to ſuffer and give a teſtimony unto his Truth. Our Covenant doth no leſſe oblige us to ſuffering, than to doing; and it is the ignorance or ineffectuall conſideration of our dutie that makes us thus to wipe our mouthes, as if we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42734:9"/> had done nothing worthy of rebuke: Neither yet doth it excuſe, that ſome were not active to obtani Protections, the receiving of them was to proſtitute the chaſtitie of that affection which we owe unto the Cauſe of GOD, and could be no better than a bribe that blinds the eyes of the wiſe, and hinders from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judgement unto the afflicted.</p>
            <p>The deep apprehenſion of their ſouls danger, moves us ſeriouſly, and in the bowels of JESUS CHRIST, to intreat all Temporizers and Back-ſliders to remember whence they are fallen, and to repent: Let it not be a light thing unto ſuch, that they have deſpiſed the Oath of GOD, under-valued the precious Truth of the Goſpel and drawne upon themſelves the guilt of their Brethrens blood, by forſaking them in their juſt defence. If the due ſenſe of their ſin ſhall bring them to lament after the Lord, they may hope to finde him gracious and mercifull, to forgive their iniquity, and heal their back-ſlidings: But if they ſhall harden themſelves, and continue in their provocation, they have cauſe of fear that the Lord of Hoſtes ſhal avenge the quarrell of his Covenant upon them who have ſworn falſely by his Name.</p>
            <p>Yet is it not that thoſe alone have cauſe to mourn; All the Land have done fooliſhly, and provoked the holy One of Iſrael unto wrath: The Lord hath been glorious in the midſt of us, but who hath regarded his work, or conſidered the operation of his hands? Though he hath been liberall in the offer of his love, yet few have believed the Goſpel, and ſtudied to walk worthy of the name: JESUS CHRIST hath neither been known nor honoured; who hath valued him in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42734:9"/> the excellencie of his Perſon, or imployed him in the vertue of his Offices? Holy duties have been negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and piety and godlineſſe reproached: Is there not cauſe to lament for the Atheiſme, ignorance of GOD, blaſpheming of his Name, ſwearing by them that are no gods, intemperancie, uncleanneſſe, deceit, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that prevailes amongſt many? And ſhould not our eyes run down with tears, becauſe of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, ſelf-ſeeking, and obſtructing of Juſtice amongſt our Judges, becauſe of rioting and exceſſe, ſpoyling and oppreſſing amongſt our Souldiours, becauſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence and profanitie amongſt Miniſters, becauſe of murmurings &amp; grudgings, deep ſecuritiy, carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, neutralitie, &amp; lukewarmneſſe almoſt amongſt all. The Covenant which hath been attended by a ſtately work of more than ordinary providence, and ſealed with many rich and precious bleſſings from Heaven, is by many under-valued and ſet at naught; nay, by ſome blaſphemed, as an accurſed and unholy thing. Becauſe of thoſe things, thouſands have fallen by the Sword, and ten thouſands by the Peſtilence, our high-wayes are deſolate, and our Cities left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inhabitants, the like hath not been heard in our dayes, nor in the dayes of our Fathers: And <hi>yet the wrath of the Lord is not turned away, but his hand is ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out ſtill.</hi> O that men were wiſe to <hi>hear the voice of the rod, and who hath appointed it!</hi> Shall we continue to tempt the moſt High, and ſtrive with our Maker until he make an end of us? <hi>Let us confeſſe our iniquity, and be humbled for our ſin, let us ſow to our ſelves in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and reap in mercy, let us break up our fallow ground, for it is time to ſeek the Lord, untill he come and rain righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42734:10"/>
            <p>We cannot but from the ſenſe of thoſe judgements that lyes heavy upon the Land, and from that wrath that ſtill threatens us, warne every man to repent and ſet on to duty. Let Rulers and Judges do judgment, and execute Juſtice without reſpect of perſons: Let Officers and Souldiours live ſoberly, do violence to no man, and more minde the Cauſe of GOD, than their own advantage: Let Paſtors feed the flock of CHRIST in love, be zealous in advancing the Work of Reformation, and purging of the Houſe of GOD: And let every one in his ſtation, minde thoſe things whereunto the Lord hath called him. Though we be afflicted and ſore broken, yet if wee return unto the Lord, he will have mercy on us, and heal us; Hath he not already begun to revive us, and to raiſe us up?</p>
            <p>It is a mercy worthy to be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that in the day of the power &amp; pride of our cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and inſolent Enemies, the Lord ſhould have ſhewed himſelf glorious &amp; mighty, to give victory &amp; ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his people, when our hopes were near gone: We were in a low condition, not onely at the weakeſt, but even at the worſt, under the guilt of many provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, repining againſt the Lord, and haſting to the pathes of the Deſtroyer: yet the Preſerver of men had regard unto us, to keep us from deſtruction, and to eaſe and avenge us of many of our adverſaries, whoſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes he made as dung unto the earth in the day of his fury and indignation. If after ſo great a mercy, any ſhould bee found amongſt us to turn away from the Lord, and again to ſubmit unto, or comply with the Enemies of his Truth, they could not but ſin againſt their own ſouls, and provoke the eyes of his glory
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42734:10"/> until there were no remedy. We beſeech all the Lords People throughout the Land, nay we Charge them before GOD and the Lord JESUS CHRIST, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead, to hold faſt the Truth in love, to have regard to the glory of the Son of GOD, the excellency of the Goſpel, the ſacred and inviolable Bond of the Covenant, the beauty of the Work of Reformation, and the worth of a good Conſcience, above all earthly loſſes and advantages; and from the due ſenſe and apprehenſion of thoſe things, to arme themſelves with ſtrong reſolutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the degrees of back-ſliding or complying with the Enemy; That they be no more as Reeds ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the winde; but that they may give a proof of their Faith, Patience and Courage, in the midſt of all the difficulties and ſtraits which they ſhall meet with. Every one who knowes the Lord, will cleave to their duty, and wait for his ſalvation: <hi>He is faithful, and will not ſuffer us to be tempted above that we are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that we may be able to bear it. The rod of the wicked ſhall not reſt too long upon the lot of the righteous.</hi> But <hi>when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon mount Zion and upon Jeruſalem, he will puniſh the fruit of the ſtout heart</hi> of the proud Enemy, and bring down <hi>the glory of his high looks:</hi> Then ſhall all the haters of Zion be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and confounded, but the Lords People ſhall be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42734:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42734:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
